{"test_questions": [[{"question": "A nozzle is said to be a convergent nozzle", "opta": "when the cross-section of the nozzle increases continuously from entrance to exit", "optb": "when the cross-section of the nozzle decreases continuously from entrance to exit", "optc": "when the cross-section of the nozzle first decreases from entrance to throat and then increases from its throat to exit", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A turbine is said to have an axial discharge when the steam leaves the blade tip at __________ to the direction of the blade motion.", "opta": "60\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "180\u00b0", "optd": "270\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The flow through a nozzle is regarded as", "opta": "constant volume flow", "optb": "constant pressure flow", "optc": "isothermal flow", "optd": "isentropic flow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of total useful heat drop to the total isentropic heat drop, is called", "opta": "stage efficiency", "optb": "internal efficiency", "optc": "Rankine efficiency", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure at which the steam leaves the nozzle is known as back pressure.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge of steam in a convergent-divergent nozzle __________ after the throat (i.e. in the divergent portion of the nozzle)", "opta": "remains constant", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of discharge through the nozzle __________ when the exit pressure is gradually reduced.", "opta": "remains same", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The velocity of steam leaving the nozzle (V) is given by (where K = Nozzle coefficient or nozzle efficiency, and hd = Enthalpy or heat drop during expansion of steam in a nozzle)", "opta": "V = 44.72 hd K", "optb": "V = 44.72 K hd", "optc": "V = 44.72 K hd", "optd": "V = 44.72 K hd", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a nozzle, whole frictional loss is assumed to occur between", "opta": "inlet and thoroat", "optb": "inlet and outlet", "optc": "throat and exit", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure ratio for initially wet steam is", "opta": "0.546", "optb": "0.577", "optc": "0.582", "optd": "0.601", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The isentropic enthalpy drop in moving blade is two-third of the isentropic enthalpy drop in fixed blades of a turbine. The degree of reaction will be", "opta": "0.4", "optb": "0.56", "optc": "0.67", "optd": "1.67", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The impulse reaction turbine has its driving force", "opta": "as an impulsive force", "optb": "as a reaction force", "optc": "partly as an impulsive force and partly as a reaction force", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of reaction turbine is maximum when (where \u03b1 = Angle made by the absolute velocity (V) at inlet)", "opta": "Vb = 0.5 V cos \u03b1", "optb": "Vb = V cos \u03b1", "optc": "Vb = 0.5 V2 cos \u03b1", "optd": "Vb = V2 cos \u03b1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A regenerative steam cycle renders", "opta": "increased work output per unit mass of steam", "optb": "decreased work output per unit mass of steam", "optc": "increased thermal efficiency", "optd": "decreased work output per unit mass of steam as well as increased thermal efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "De-Laval turbine is a", "opta": "single rotor impulse turbine", "optb": "multi-rotor impulse turbine", "optc": "impulse reaction turbine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The turbine, in which the general direction of the steam flow is parallel to the turbine axis, is called axial flow turbines", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure gives the velocity of steam at the throat equal to the velocity of sound.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reheat factor is the ratio of the", "opta": "cumulative heat drop to the isentropic heat drop", "optb": "isentropic heat drop to the heat supplied", "optc": "total useful heat drop to the total isentropic heat drop", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The turbine blades do not change the direction of steam issuing from the nozzle.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal equilibrium means that the flow of steam is", "opta": "isothermal", "optb": "isentropic", "optc": "hyperbolic", "optd": "polytropic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the back pressure of a nozzle is below the designed value of pressure at exit of nozzle, the nozzle is said to be", "opta": "choked", "optb": "underdamping", "optc": "overdamping", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the workdone on the blades to the energy supplied to the blades, is called", "opta": "blading efficiency", "optb": "nozzle efficiency", "optc": "gross or stage efficiency", "optd": "mechanical efficiency", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge is __________ at critical pressure.", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The supersaturated flow of steam through a nozzle as compared to a stable flow, the available heat drop", "opta": "remains the same", "optb": "increases", "optc": "decreases", "optd": "is unpredictable", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steam leaves the nozzle at a", "opta": "high pressure and a low velocity", "optb": "high pressure and a high velocity", "optc": "low pressure and a low velocity", "optd": "low pressure and a high velocity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure gives the velocity of steam at the throat", "opta": "equal to the velocity of sound", "optb": "less than the velocity of sound", "optc": "more than the velocity of sound", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Parsons' reaction turbine has", "opta": "only moving blades", "optb": "only fixed blades", "optc": "identical fixed and moving blades", "optd": "fixed and moving blades of different shape", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The action of steam in a steam turbine is", "opta": "static", "optb": "dynamic", "optc": "static and dynamic", "optd": "neither static nor dynamic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The blade velocity coefficient is ratio of relative velocity of steam at outlet tip of the blade to the relative velocity of steam at inlet tip of the blade.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Multi-stage steam turbines are of the", "opta": "velocity compounded type", "optb": "reaction type", "optc": "pressure compounded type", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure ratio (p2/p1) is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In reaction turbines, the axial thrust is due to", "opta": "pressure drop across the rotor", "optb": "change in axial velocity", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "The expansion of steam in a nozzle follows Rankine cycle.", "optb": "The friction in the nozzle increases the dryness fraction of steam.", "optc": "The pressure of steam at throat is called critical pressure.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A binary vapour plant consists of", "opta": "steam turbine", "optb": "steam condenser", "optc": "mercury boiler", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a De-Laval nozzle expanding superheated steam from 10 bar to 0.1 bar, the pressure at the minimum cross-section (i. e. pressure at throat, p2) will be", "opta": "3.3 bar", "optb": "5.46 bar", "optc": "8.2 bar", "optd": "9.9 bar", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stage efficiency (\u03b7S) is given by (where \u03b7B = Blading efficiency, and \u03b7N = Nozzle efficiency)", "opta": "\u03b7S = \u03b7B x \u03b7N", "optb": "\u03b7S = \u03b7B/\u03b7N", "optc": "\u03b7S = \u03b7N/\u03b7B", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure ratio for initially dry saturated steam is more as compared to initially wet steam.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a convergent divergent nozzle, the discharge depends upon the initial conditions of steam and the area of nozzle at throat.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Parson's reaction turbine is a __________ reaction turbine.", "opta": "40 percent", "optb": "50 percent", "optc": "60 percent", "optd": "70 percent", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The turbine blades are", "opta": "straight", "optb": "circular", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The variation of steam pressure in the nozzle depends upon", "opta": "velocity of steam", "optb": "specific volume of steam", "optc": "dryness fraction of steam", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Steam turbines are used for", "opta": "large marine propulsion", "optb": "electric power generation", "optc": "direct drive of fans, compressors, pumps", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Parson's turbine is a", "opta": "simple impulse turbine", "optb": "simple reaction turbine", "optc": "impulse-reaction turbine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of the reheat factor varies from", "opta": "1.02 to 1.06", "optb": "1.08 to 1.l0", "optc": "1.2 to 1.6", "optd": "1.6 to 2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steam enters the nozzle at a", "opta": "high pressure and a low velocity", "optb": "high pressure and a high velocity", "optc": "low pressure and a low velocity", "optd": "low pressure and a high velocity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference of supersaturated temperature and saturation temperature at that pressure is called", "opta": "degree of supersaturation", "optb": "degree of superheat", "optc": "degree of undercooling", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum efficiency of a reaction turbine is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the useful heat drop to the isentropic heat drop is called", "opta": "condenser efficiency", "optb": "nozzle efficiency", "optc": "boiler efficiency", "optd": "vacuum efficiency", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of steam turbines may be improved by", "opta": "reheating of steam", "optb": "regenerative feed heating", "optc": "binary vapour plant", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reaction turbine, when steam flows through the fixed blades,", "opta": "pressure increases while velocity decreases", "optb": "pressure decreases while velocity increases", "optc": "pressure and velocity both decreases", "optd": "pressure and velocity both increases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}